When I was a kid, I was the quintessential nerd.
عندما كنت صغيراً، كنت شغوفاً بالدراسة
I think some of you were, too.
أظن أن بعضاً منكم كان كذلك، أيضاًً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And you, sir, who laughed the loudest, you probably still are.
و أنت يا سيدي، الذي ضحكت بشدة، من المحتمل أنك مازلت كذلك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I grew up in a small town in the dusty plains of north Texas,
لقد عشت في بلدة صغيرة في أحد ضواحي نورث تكساس،
the son of a sheriff who was the son of a pastor.
كوني ولداً لضابط في الشرطة وهو حفيد لقس.
Getting into trouble was not an option.
فإن الوقوع في المشاكل لم يكن من خياراتي.
And so I started reading calculus books for fun.
فبدأت بقراءة كتب الرياضيات للترفيه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You did, too.
أنتم فعلتم ذلك، أيضاً.
That led me to building a laser and a computer and model rockets,
قادني ذلك لعمل ليزر وحاسوب ونماذج صواريخ،
and that led me to making rocket fuel in my bedroom.
فأنشأت ورشة صواريخ في غرفة نومي.
Now, in scientific terms,
الآن، علمياً،
we call this a very bad idea.
نسمي هذه بالفكرة السيئة جداً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Around that same time,
في ذلك الوقت،
Stanley Kubrick's "2001: A Space Odyssey" came to the theaters,
رواية ستاني كوبورز "ملحمة الفضاء" أصبحت في دور العرض،
and my life was forever changed.
وبذلك تغيرت حياتي للأبد.
I loved everything about that movie,
لقد أحببت كل شيء في ذلك الفلم،
especially the HAL 9000.
خصوصي "هال" 9000.
Now, HAL was a sentient computer
"هال" كان حاسوباً واعياً
designed to guide the Discovery spacecraft
مصمماً لقيادة سفينة الاستكشاف
from the Earth to Jupiter.
من الأرض إلى المشترى.
HAL was also a flawed character,
"هال" كان شخصيةً سيئة،
for in the end he chose to value the mission over human life.
في النهاية لقد اختار إتمام المهمة عوضاً عن إنقاذ البشرية.
Now, HAL was a fictional character,
"هال" كان شخصيةً خياليََة،
but nonetheless he speaks to our fears,
لكن ومع ذلك لقد تحاكى مع مخاوفنا،
our fears of being subjugated
مخاوفنا في التعامل مع
by some unfeeling, artificial intelligence
ذكاء اصطناعي عديم المشاعر
who is indifferent to our humanity.
لا يختلف عنا نحن البشر.
I believe that such fears are unfounded.
أنا أؤمن بأن هذه المخاوف لا وجود لها.
Indeed, we stand at a remarkable time
في الواقع، نحن نعيش وقتاً مميزاً
in human history,
في تاريخ البشريََة،
where, driven by refusal to accept the limits of our bodies and our minds,
حيث نسير رافضين وضع حدود لقدراتنا العقلية والجسدية،
we are building machines
نقوم ببناء آلات
of exquisite, beautiful complexity and grace
ذات تعقيد وأداء رائعين وجميلين
that will extend the human experience
ستسهم في توسيع المعرفة البشريََة
in ways beyond our imagining.
لمراحل لا يمكن تصورها.
After a career that led me from the Air Force Academy
عبر خبرتي المهنية من الكلية الجوية
to Space Command to now,
إلى توجيه سفن الفضاء، إلى الوقت الحالي،
I became a systems engineer,
أصبحت مهندس أنظمة،
and recently I was drawn into an engineering problem
ومؤخراً تم توكيلي بمهمة حل مشكلة هندسية
associated with NASA's mission to Mars.
متعلََقة بعملية وكالة الفضاء "ناسا" في المريخ.
Now, in space flights to the Moon,
حالياً، في الرحلات الفضائية إلى القمر،
we can rely upon mission control in Houston
يمكننا الإعتماد على نظام الملاحة المسمََى "هيوستون"
to watch over all aspects of a flight.
لمتابعة كافة تفاصيل الرحلة.
However, Mars is 200 times further away,
ولكن المريخ يبعد مئتي ضعف مقارنة بالقمر،
and as a result it takes on average 13 minutes
وبالتالي نحتاج في المتوسط ل 13 دقيقة
for a signal to travel from the Earth to Mars.
لتنتقل الإشارة من الأرض إلى المريخ،
If there's trouble, there's not enough time.
وإذا ما حدثت مشكلة، لا يوجد وقت كاف لتفاديها.
And so a reasonable engineering solution
ولذلك فإن الحل الهندسي الأكثر فائدة
calls for us to put mission control
يدعونا لوضع جهاز توجيه للحركة (جهاز ملاحة)
inside the walls of the Orion spacecraft.
داخل جدران المركبة الفضائية.
Another fascinating idea in the mission profile
وفكرة أخرى جميلة تصب في مجال أداء العملية
places humanoid robots on the surface of Mars
هي إرسال رجال آليين ووضعهم فوق سطح المريخ
before the humans themselves arrive,
قبل وصول البشر بنفسهم إلى هناك،
first to build facilities
أولاً لتقديم بعض التسهيلات
and later to serve as collaborative members of the science team.
ومن ثمََ كأعضاء متعاونين في الفريق العلمي.
Now, as I looked at this from an engineering perspective,
حالياًً عندما أتمعن في هذه الفكرة من منظور هندسي،
it became very clear to me that what I needed to architect
فإنني أرى بشكل واضح أن ما أخطط له
was a smart, collaborative,
هو حل ذكي، متعاون،
socially intelligent artificial intelligence.
يتمتع بالذكاء الاصطناعي والاجتماعي.
In other words, I needed to build something very much like a HAL
بعبارة أخرى، أريد بناء ما يشبه "هال" إلى حد كبير
but without the homicidal tendencies.
ولكن بدون أن يكون له نزعات للقتل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Let's pause for a moment.
لنتوقف للحظة.
Is it really possible to build an artificial intelligence like that?
هل من الممكن بناء نظام ذكي مثل هذا؟
Actually, it is.
في الواقع، أجل.
In many ways,
بتصورات مختلفة،
this is a hard engineering problem
إن هذه مشكلة هندسية صعبة
with elements of AI,
تضمن عناصر ذكاء اصطناعي،
not some wet hair ball of an AI problem that needs to be engineered.
ليست مجرد مسألة ذكاء اصطناعي بسيطة يمكن إنشاؤها.
To paraphrase Alan Turing,
كما ورد عن "آلان تورنج"،
I'm not interested in building a sentient machine.
أنا لست مهتما بآلة ذات إحساس.
I'm not building a HAL.
أنا لا أقوم بصناعة "هال".
All I'm after is a simple brain,
كل ما أريد إنجازه هو مجرد عقل بسيط،
something that offers the illusion of intelligence.
يمكنه تقديم هذا الذكاء الخيالي.
The art and the science of computing have come a long way
إن علوم وفنون الحاسوب قد أثمرت في نهاية المطاف
since HAL was onscreen,
منذ ظهور "هال" على الشاشة،
and I'd imagine if his inventor Dr. Chandra were here today,
وأظن في حال وجود المخترع الدكتور "شاندرو" هنا اليوم،
he'd have a whole lot of questions for us.
فإنه سوف يكون لديه العديد من التساؤلات.
Is it really possible for us
هل بالفعل يمكننا
to take a system of millions upon millions of devices,
تكوين نظام يحوي ملايين ملايين الأجهزة،
to read in their data streams,
يمكنه قراءة معطياتها،
to predict their failures and act in advance?
التنبؤ بحالات حصول الخطأ، و التصرف قبل وقوعه؟
Yes.
أجل.
Can we build systems that converse with humans in natural language?
هل يمكننا بناء نظام يمكنه التحاكي مع البشر بلغاتهم؟
Yes.
أجل.
Can we build systems that recognize objects, identify emotions,
هل يمكننا بناء أنظمة يمكنها التعرف على الأجسام، وعلى حركتها،
emote themselves, play games and even read lips?
والشعور بأنفسها، أو اللعب بألعاب الحاسب وقراءة حركة الشفاه؟
Yes.
أجل.
Can we build a system that sets goals,
هل يمكننا بناء نظام يضع أهدافاًً لنفسه،
that carries out plans against those goals and learns along the way?
يتوجب الوصول إليها وضع خطط يتعلمها حتى يصل هدفه؟
Yes.
أجل.
Can we build systems that have a theory of mind?
هل يمكننا بناء أنظمة تستطيع التفكير؟
This we are learning to do.
هذا ما نقوم بالتعلم لإنجازه.
Can we build systems that have an ethical and moral foundation?
هل يمكننا بناء أنظمة ذات اعتقادات أدبية وخُلقية؟
This we must learn how to do.
هذا ما يتوجب علينا تعلم كيفية إنجازه.
So let's accept for a moment
إذا، لنتقبَََل حالياً
that it's possible to build such an artificial intelligence
القدرة على بناء نظام كهذا
for this kind of mission and others.
من أجل مهمة كهذه وغيرها.
The next question you must ask yourself is,
السؤال الآخر الذي ينبغي عليكم سؤاله هو،
should we fear it?
هل ينبغي علينا الخوف منه؟
Now, every new technology
حسناً، كل تقنية جديدة
brings with it some measure of trepidation.
تجلب معها شيئاً من الريبة.
When we first saw cars,
عندما رأينا السيارات لأول مرة،
people lamented that we would see the destruction of the family.
توقع البشر حدوث دمار للعائلة.
When we first saw telephones come in,
عندما رأينا الهواتف لأول مرة،
people were worried it would destroy all civil conversation.
قلق الناس من قيامها بإنهاء المحادثات الشخصية.
At a point in time we saw the written word become pervasive,
في الماضي عندما انتشرت الكلمة المكتوبة،
people thought we would lose our ability to memorize.
ظن البشر أننا سنفقد قدرتنا على التذكر.
These things are all true to a degree,
هذه التنبؤات واقعية لحد معين،
but it's also the case that these technologies
ولكن هذه التقنيات
brought to us things that extended the human experience
جلبت لنا ما زاد خبرتنا كبشر
in some profound ways.
بطرقٍ عميقة.
So let's take this a little further.
لنتوسع في هذه النقطة بعض الشيء.
I do not fear the creation of an AI like this,
أنا لا أخاف من بناء أنظمة ذكاء اصطناعي كهذه،
because it will eventually embody some of our values.
ﻷنها بالنتيجة ستقوم باستعمال معاييرنا.
Consider this: building a cognitive system is fundamentally different
لنأخذ بعين الاعتبار أن بناء نظام واع يختلف تماماً
than building a traditional software-intensive system of the past.
عن بناء النظام التقليدي المعقد في الماضي.
We don't program them. We teach them.
نحن لا نقوم ببرمجتها، نحن نعلِِمها.
In order to teach a system how to recognize flowers,
لتعليم نظام كيف يتعرف على الورود،
I show it thousands of flowers of the kinds I like.
أُريه آلاف الورود، من الأنواع المفضلة لدي.
In order to teach a system how to play a game --
لتعليم نظام كيف يلعب لعبة
Well, I would. You would, too.
حسنا، أريد فعل ذلك. و أنتم تريدون، أيضاً.
I like flowers. Come on.
أنا أحب الورود، صدقوني.
To teach a system how to play a game like Go,
لتعليم نظام كيفية لعب لعبة ك "جو"،
I'd have it play thousands of games of Go,
أقوم بلعب ال "جو" آلاف المرات،
but in the process I also teach it
ضمنياً أقوم بتعليمه التمييز
how to discern a good game from a bad game.
بين اللعبة الجيدة من السيئة.
If I want to create an artificially intelligent legal assistant,
إذا أردت إنشاء مساعد قانوني ذكي،
I will teach it some corpus of law
سوف أعلمه بعض قواعد القانون
but at the same time I am fusing with it
ولكن بنفس الوقت أقوم بتمرير
the sense of mercy and justice that is part of that law.
إحساس الرحمة والعدل المتعلق بهذا القانون.
In scientific terms, this is what we call ground truth,
علمياً نطلق على هذه العملية "القاعدة الحقيقية"،
and here's the important point:
هنا تكمن النقطة المهمة:
in producing these machines,
لإنشاء آلات كهذه،
we are therefore teaching them a sense of our values.
نحن نقوم بتعليمها الشعور بقيمنا.
To that end, I trust an artificial intelligence
إلى هنا، أنا أثق بالذكاء الاصطناعي
the same, if not more, as a human who is well-trained.
بما يساوي، إن لم يزِد، إنساناً جيد التدريب.
But, you may ask,
لكن، قد تسألون،
what about rogue agents,
ماذا عن العملاء المحتالين،
some well-funded nongovernment organization?
المؤسسات غير الحكومية ذات الدعم المادي القوي؟
I do not fear an artificial intelligence in the hand of a lone wolf.
أنا لا أخاف من الذكاء الاصطناعي في يد ثعلب وحيد.
Clearly, we cannot protect ourselves against all random acts of violence,
بشكل صريح، لا يمكننا حماية أنفسنا من كافة أشكال العنف،
but the reality is such a system
لكن في الواقع نظام كهذا
requires substantial training and subtle training
يحتاج لإنجاز تدريبات كثيفة ومعقدة
far beyond the resources of an individual.
تفوق قدرة الفرد الواحد.
And furthermore,
أيضاًً،
it's far more than just injecting an internet virus to the world,
إنها أصعب من مجرد إدخال فايروس إلى العالم عبر الإنترنت،
where you push a button, all of a sudden it's in a million places
حيث بضغطة زر، ينتشر في ملايين الأجهزة
and laptops start blowing up all over the place.
وتتعطل الحواسيب المحمولة في كل مكان.
Now, these kinds of substances are much larger,
إن هذه الأمور أكبر بكثير،
and we'll certainly see them coming.
ونحن نراها في المستقبل.
Do I fear that such an artificial intelligence
هل أخاف من هكذا ذكاء اصطناعي
might threaten all of humanity?
قد يهدد البشرية جمعاء؟
If you look at movies such as "The Matrix," "Metropolis,"
إذا ما تابعتم أفلام ك "ماتريكس"، و"شرطة القطار"
"The Terminator," shows such as "Westworld,"
و"المدمر"، ومسلسلات مثل "العالم الغربي"
they all speak of this kind of fear.
فإن كلها تتحدث عن هذه المخاوف.
Indeed, in the book "Superintelligence" by the philosopher Nick Bostrom,
في الواقع، في كتاب "الذكاء الخارق" للفيلسوف "نيك بوستروم"،
he picks up on this theme
يتناول هذه النمطية
and observes that a superintelligence might not only be dangerous,
ويرى أن الذكاء الخارق ليس مجرد خطر فحسب،
it could represent an existential threat to all of humanity.
وإنما يمكن أن يمثل تهديداً حقيقياً لكافة البشرية.
Dr. Bostrom's basic argument
الجدل الأساسي للدكتور "بوستروم"
is that such systems will eventually
أن هذه الأنظمة بشكل مفاجيء
have such an insatiable thirst for information
ستصبح متعطشة بشكل شديد للمعلومات
that they will perhaps learn how to learn
وبالتالي سوف تتعلم كيف تتم عملية التعلم
and eventually discover that they may have goals
ومن ثم تكتشف أن لديها أهدافاً
that are contrary to human needs.
تخالف ما يحتاجه البشر.
Dr. Bostrom has a number of followers.
الدكتور "بوستروم" لديه عدد من الأتباع.
He is supported by people such as Elon Musk and Stephen Hawking.
و يدعمه في تفكيره أشخاص ك "إيلون موسك" و "ستيفن هاوكنج".
With all due respect
مع كل احترامي
to these brilliant minds,
لهذه العقول الرائعة،
I believe that they are fundamentally wrong.
إلا أني أؤمن بأنهم على خطأ.
Now, there are a lot of pieces of Dr. Bostrom's argument to unpack,
هناك العديد من جدليات الدكتور "بوستوم" للمناقشة،
and I don't have time to unpack them all,
وليس لدي وقت كاف لمناقشتها كلها،
but very briefly, consider this:
لكن بشكل مختصر، فكروا في هذه:
super knowing is very different than super doing.
المعرفة الفائقة تختلف بشكل أساسي عن العمل الخارق.
HAL was a threat to the Discovery crew
"هال" كان خطراً على فريق الاستكشاف
only insofar as HAL commanded all aspects of the Discovery.
فقط عندما قام "هال" بإصدار التعليمات كافة في عملية الاستكشاف.
So it would have to be with a superintelligence.
لذا هذه الفكرة مرتبطة بالذكاء الخارق.
It would have to have dominion over all of our world.
من الممكن أن تسيطر على عالمنا.
This is the stuff of Skynet from the movie "The Terminator"
هذه الأشياء مقتبسة من فلم "المدمر"
in which we had a superintelligence
حيث لدينا ذكاء خارق
that commanded human will,
يقود رغبة البشر،
that directed every device that was in every corner of the world.
يتحكم بكل جهاز موجود في كل زاوية في أنحاء العالم.
Practically speaking,
للحديث بشكل عملي،
it ain't gonna happen.
هذا لن يحدث.
We are not building AIs that control the weather,
نحن لا نقوم ببناء أنظمة ذكاء اصطناعي تتحكم بحالة الطقس،
that direct the tides,
وتوجه المد والجزر،
that command us capricious, chaotic humans.
وتأمرنا نحن البشر المتقلبين العشوائيين.
And furthermore, if such an artificial intelligence existed,
وللمزيد، إذا وُجدت أنظمة ذكاء اصطناعي كهذه،
it would have to compete with human economies,
ستنافس اقتصاد البشر،
and thereby compete for resources with us.
وبالتالي تنافس البشر في المصادر والثروات.
And in the end --
وفي النهاية.
don't tell Siri this --
لا تخبروا نظام "سيري" بهذا
we can always unplug them.
حيث يمكننا إطفاؤها دائماً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We are on an incredible journey
نحن في رحلة عظيمة
of coevolution with our machines.
من التطور مع آلاتنا.
The humans we are today
ما نحن عليه اليوم كبشر
are not the humans we will be then.
يختلف عن ما سنكون عليه في المستقبل.
To worry now about the rise of a superintelligence
القلق الآن من نمو الذكاء الخارق
is in many ways a dangerous distraction
هو إلهاء خطير بحالات متعددة
because the rise of computing itself
لأن نمو الحوسبة بذاتها
brings to us a number of human and societal issues
يجلب لنا عدداً من المشاكل البشرية والاجتماعية
to which we must now attend.
ينبغي علينا حلها الآن.
How shall I best organize society
كيف يمكنني أن أنظم المجتمع بالشكل الأفضل
when the need for human labor diminishes?
عندما يقل احتياج اليد العاملة البشرية؟
How can I bring understanding and education throughout the globe
كيف يمكنني أن أجلب الوعي والتعليم لكافة أنحاء الأرض
and still respect our differences?
مع احترام كافة أشكال اختلافاتنا؟
How might I extend and enhance human life through cognitive healthcare?
كيف يمكنني أن أوسع وأحسن حياة الإنسان من خلال العناية الإدراكية؟
How might I use computing
كيف يمكنني استعمال الحوسبة
to help take us to the stars?
لتقوم بأخذنا إلى النجوم؟
And that's the exciting thing.
وهذا هو الشيء الممتع.
The opportunities to use computing
إن الفرص لاستعمال الحوسبة
to advance the human experience
لتطوير خبرة الإنسان
are within our reach,
في متناول يدنا،
here and now,
هنا والآن،
and we are just beginning.
نحن نبدأ فحسب.
Thank you very much.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)